Guide to the Robert Livingston papers 1974.018
Brooklyn Historical Society
Robert Livingston papers
1670-1797
Brooklyn Historical Society
Livingston, Robert (1708-1790)
New York (State). Commissioners of Indian Affairs
Livingston family
Livingston, Robert, 1654-1728
Livingston, Robert R., 1746-1813
1974.018
0.42 Linear Feet in one manuscript box.
The collection spans the period 1670 to 1797 and contains legal documents and correspondence related to Robert Livingston (1654-1728) of Albany and his estate, Livingston Manor.
Box 1
Scope and Contents
This collection spans the period 1670 to 1797 and contains legal documents and correspondence related to Robert Livingston of Albany and his estate, Livingston Manor. Folder 27 includes two letters exchanged between Robert R. Livingston, Chancellor of New York, and his relative Robert Livingston (1708-1790), Third Lord of Livingston Manor, regarding a dispute over the estate. Also included in the collection are propositions, minutes, examinations, accounts, journals, and correspondence, including a selection of transactions between the Commissioners of Indian Affairs at Albany and the Indigenous peoples of the Hudson Valley and central New York. Materials in the collection are primarily in English, though some are also in Dutch. Most items are original, with some early copies. Many items are in fragile condition.
Biographical Note
Robert Livingston (1654-1728), was an influential businessman and politician in colonial Albany, N.Y. Also known as Robert Livingston the Elder, he was of the first generation of the prominent Livingston family of New York State. Born in Scotland, Livingston spent many years in Holland, where he acquired the Dutch language and customs. He moved to Albany in 1673, and was shortly appointed town clerk and secretary of the board of commissioners for Indian Affairs. In 1686, he received a patent for land comprising the present-day New York counties of Columbia and Dutchess, on which he built his family home, Livingston Manor. In 1709 he represented the district of Albany in the Assembly and in 1718 was elected speaker. He functioned as secretary of Indian Affairs from the 1670s on, officially from 1696 to 1710, at which time he relinquished this post to his nephew, Robert Livingston, Jr. (1663-1725). Robert Livingston the Elder retired in 1725. Certain of his descendents played instrumental roles in the political life of colonial New York City and the founding of the United States. His grandson, Philip Livingston (1716-1778), for whom Brooklyn's Livingston Street is named, was a New York delegate to the Continental Congress and the only Brooklyn resident to sign the Declaration of Independence. His great-grandson, Robert R. Livingston (1746-1813), served as Recorder of New York City and was the first Chancellor of New York, as well as the first U.S. Secretary for Foreign Affairs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sylvia A. Livingston, 1890.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
Series 1: Livingston Manor is arranged chronologically.
Series 2: Five Nations Documents is arranged chronologically.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Manors -- New York (State); Indians of North America -- New York (State); Journals (accounts); Minutes; Indians of North America -- New York (State) -- Government relations; Albany (N.Y.); Decedents' estates -- New York (State); New York (State) -- Politics and government; Indians of North America -- Canada; Livingston Manor (N.Y.); Deeds; Land titles -- New York (State); Bills of sale; New York (State) -- Surveys; Land grants -- New York (State); Legal documents; Correspondence; Accounts; Agreements; Livingston, Robert (1708-1790); New York (State). Commissioners of Indian Affairs; Livingston, Robert, 1654-1728; Livingston family; Livingston, Robert R., 1746-1813
- Series 1: Livingston Manor
  - Deed of gift for the Robert Livingston Manor papers, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Minutes of a meeting of Long Island Historical Society Directors, with remarks by Benjamin D. Silliman, introducing an essay by Edward F. De Lancey of New York on the historical background of the Livingston papers.
  - Processing note on envelope, unknown origin (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill of sale by Keeseway, 1670 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Bill of sale by Keeseway of the land named Potamkasik Patkock and Stichsoock to Brandt van Slichtenhorst on behalf of the patroon of Rensselaerswyck, 27 May 1649, a margin note of 20 July 1649, and Notarial record confirming the aforesaid sale, 15 June 1670, being early, signed copies on one sheet, all in Dutch, re: "Landt op Claverack;" each part with note in English, "A True Copy," signed by Robert Livingston, Secretary; the Bill of sale signed by Mahikan Indians Keeseway and Skinaias, and by Brandt van Slichtenhorst, director of Rensselaerswyck, and Johannis Megapolensis, Pastor; Notarialrecord mentions Ludovicus Cobes, secretary of the Albany colony of Rensselaerswyck and Schenectady, and is signed by Keeseway, Anahamet, Andries Toller, Jeremias Van Rensselaer; Barent Pieterse [Coeymans?], and Joris Christoffersen [?].
  - Petition, by Robert Livingston of Albany, to Governor Edmund Andros / Andross, 1680 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Petition, by Robert Livingston of Albany, to Governor Edmund Andros / Andross, at New York, for the grant of a patent to purchase land lying upon the Kill of Roeloff Jansen or Johnson, the land being "upon the East Syde of Hudson's River noord Catts Kill" and being diposed of by the Indian proprietors.
  - Bills of Sale, 1683 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    (2 items) Bill of sale, for the land of Roeloff Jansen or Johnson's Kill, from the Indian proprietors to Robert Livingston, with translations in English and Dutch; mentions Johannes Provoost, and Jan Janse Bleecker, Commissioner of Albany Colony of Rensselaerswyck and Schenectady, and includes many Indian names.
  - List of goods, 1683 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    List of goods which Robert Livingston ("his half") is to give to the Indians in Pounds for Roeloff Jansen's Kill, accounting document, in Dutch (numbers represent guilders, not pounds) [CG]; includes map sketch of these lands, on reverse.
  - Contract document, 1684 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contract document, in Dutch: Robert Livingston (one side) and Gerritt Teunisse and Maste Cornelis (other side, and representing Dirck Wessels) partition the land farthest back of the Roeloff Jansen's Kill; Livingston chooses the ronde vlakte "circular flats" and Dirk Wessels takes the "long flats" [CG]; includes list of witnesses, including Teunis Abrahamse, Frans Hardick, Lambert Janse, Johannes Bensingh [Benson], Jacob Vosburgh, Isak Vosburgh, Frederick Claese van Drenthe, and Jacob Janse van [---][document torn at mid-fold].
  - Land grant to Robert Livingston, 1685 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Land grant to Robert Livingston for the purchase of Tachkanak, signed by Thomas Dongan (1634-1715), Governor of New York, at Fort James in New York City, with seal, dated 5 June 1685.
  - Accounting document, 1685 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Accounting document, in Dutch, list of items requested for Tachkanak behind Patkoop with a list of the items actually offered [CG], re: Robert Livingston's purchase, with map sketch on reverse, dated "Albany 9 July 1685."
  - Robert Livingston's land purchase, 1685 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    (2 items) 3 articles on 2 sheets, all in Dutch, dated Tachkanak, 1 August 1685, re: Robert Livingston's land purchase: Survey return for Tachkanak; Agreement concluded with native owners of Tachkanak, with list of items given in the transaction, signed by Joris Aertsen van den Baast, Johannis Benson and a "Teunis" who makes his mark; List of the measurements of Tachkanak [CG], with a cover note in English describing survey as the work of Samuel Libia.
  - Contract of sale, 1685 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Contract of sale, for the purchase of land at Tachkanak by Robert Livingston from the Indian proprietors, signed, with seals, at Albany, dated 10 August 1685; colonial signatories include Major Gervis Baxter commander of Albany, David Schuyler, Johannes Wendel, William Toller, Gerrit Bancker magistrate of Albany, and Robert Sanders the interpreter; Indian signatories include Tataemshatt, Machwe, Tawihaes, Niehotowaw, Minasees, Tantanenowa (wife of Netipo), and Mamattittawawpe [note variant spellings].
  - License granted to Alida Livingston, 1687-1688 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    License granted to Mrs. Alida Livingston of Albany to purchase 400 acres of land behind Tachkanak, upon Roeloff Jansen's kill, for the use of her son Phillip Livingston, made, signed and sealed by governor Thomas Dongan at Albany, dated 1 January 1687-1688.
  - Contract of sale and a list of goods, 1687-1688 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    (2 items) a Contract of sale and a List of Goods (the latter in Dutch), re: the purchase of land at Tachkanak known as Quisichkook, bought by Robert Livingston from the Indian proprietors, the contract signed at Claverack, dated 17 February 1687/8, by witnesses Johannes Benson and Herbert Jacobszen, and signed with marks and sealed by the Indians Tataemshatt, Manetipo, Nekantakos, Tatapenowa (wife of Manetipo), and Michiel (brother of Tataemshatt) [note variant spellings]; this contract later endorsed by Johannes Wendel and Levinus Van Schaick, aldermen, at Albany, on 2 June 1688, their endorsement being noted on the list of goods, signed by Robert Livingston.
  - Extract of a patent for land, 1689 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Extract of a patent for land at Roeloff Janson's Kill, unfinished and unsigned, apparently an early copy or draft, "11 Nov 1689" written at the end of the extract, refers to an agreement dated 10 July 1683, made between Robert Livingston and the Indian proprietors.
  - Purchase agreement, 1697 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Purchase agreement between Indians and Robert Livingston, re: land on Roeloff Jansen's kill, mentions Johannes Dyckman, signed and sealed at Albany by squaws My Lady and Manhagh, dated 7 July 1697, witnessed by Johannes Beeckman and Johannes Livingston, confirmed by Goose the Indian at Albany on 14 August 1697, and with appended note, unsigned, re: a complaint of 19 April 1725 made by Trioas an Indian son of Manhagh regarding the above transaction, the complaint being resolved by Robert Livingston and the sale confirmed in the presence of Justice of the Peace Jacob Vosburgh, Jan Tys Smit, Frederick Proper, and Gouwanan, an Indian.
  - Conditions by which farm land is leased, 1712 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Conditions by which farm land is leased out by Robert Livingston [CG], unsigned, dated 11 December 1712, in Dutch.
  - Land conveyance and note, 1713 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    (2 items) Note, titled "Indians convey gochkomekok and their Rights and Titles to the Mannor of Livingston Bounds," 11 May 1713, with notes on individual Indians; and, the original Conveyance, signed and sealed by 15 Indians, including the sachems Tataemshatt and Wampopoham (alias Michiel), and signed by Jacob Vosburgh, John Conrad Petry and two others, with memorandum affirming the aforesaid sale, dated 21 October 1765 and signed at Albany by Judge Rensselaer Nicoll, clerk Matthew Visscher, and witness John Conrad Petry.
  - Letter from Robert Livingston to Mrs. Rensselaer, 1716 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Letter, in Dutch, from Robert Livingston (RL) to Mrs. Rensselaer, dated 31 December 1716, requesting that they meet in a convenient place (because he is so far from the city) in order to examine and exempt the indentures (Palatines?).
  - Memorandum titled "Indians desist their Claim of Land lying near ye north Land of Mannor Livingston", 1718 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    (3 items) Copies [CG], two in Dutch and one in English, of a Memorandum titled "Indians desist their Claim of Land lying near ye north Land of Mannor Livingston", dated 13 May 1718, the original signed by Philip Livingston, Robert Livingston, interpreter Martin Vosburgh, Justice of the Peace Roelof Duytser, and Andries Brussie; the memorandum mentions Willem Enoogh, tenant Nikus Janse, surveyor John Beatty, and Indians Catharickset, his wife Nanakema, her daughter Mawemeen, her sister Shano, and her brother Kochak.
  - Land document, 1721-1722 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Land document, titled "Indians Release Waentas's Land", dated "Mannor Livingston 19 February 1721/2," re: land "lying and being at ye South end of Taghkanik hills," the release made, signed and sealed by Nepetaw, Sankewenaghik, and Corlaer (alias Unanachquin) son of Pighketay, witnessed by eight other Indians and five colonists, the Release approved of and signed by Justice of the Peace Jacob Vosburgh, mentions surveyor John Beatty [Waentas also spelled Waintas].
  - Land document, 1724 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Land document, titled "The Indians quitt Claim to Land on ye north Line of Mannor Livingston near Roeloff Jansen's kill", dated "Mannor Livingston 4 May 1724," the Quit Claim made, signed and sealed by Nameseet and Potighkamow, and witnessed by interpreter Kekughqua, Notamoss, and Akenimitt, and by Alida Vetch and Geertruyd Bayard, mentions surveyor John Beatty, Hendrick Van Rensselaer, Martin Van Dousse [var. spelled Van Dusen, or Van Deusen], Robert Van Dousse, Robert Teunis Van Dousse, Nikas Janse.
  - Land Survey, 1724 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Land Survey, by James Livingston on warrant from Governor William Burnett, with map sketch in ink and watercolor, titled "A Draft of the Land Granted to Severall Palatine head's in ye Mannor of Livingston", dated 17 October 1724, for land adjoining the Hudson River below Robert's Point, comprising 5,768 acres with an addition of 231 acres, mentions grantees Jacob Scherp, Johannes Herremer, John Coleman, and Christophell Huyendom.
  - Letters of eviction, 1766-1767 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    2 letters of eviction, from Robert Livingston Jr. to tenant William Bevin, both being contemporary or near contemporary copies drawn up at Livingston's request by Teunis Van Vechten, the originals dated 8 July 1766 and 23 March 1767.
  - Deposition made by Peter Van Den Bogart, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Deposition made by Peter Van Den Bogart, a farmer of Livingston Manor, signed at Albany on 14 July 1767 and sworn to, before Justice John Ten Eyck, re: the matter of Robert Livingston Jr. v. his tenant William Bevin, mentions Hendrick Rensselaer.
  - Articles of agreement, 1782, circa 1784 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    (2 items) Articles of agreement, made 12 April 1782, between Leonard Conine, tenant farmer of Livingston Manor, and John Laraway, setting terms of one year's rent and labor for Conine's housing of Laraway and his family, witnessed by John A. Fonda and John Bingham; and, c. 1784 accounting of rent paid by Jonathan Adams to Robert R. Livingston, at Ancram, "for Stephen Johns, for the use of his farm at Oblong," for the period 1782-1784, mentions Mr. Gray, Mr. Van Buren, Capt. Dacker, with "Alford" written at bottom of the page beside a tear, and the name of Robert R. Van Deusen written on the reverse.
  - Receipt, 1788-1796 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    (2 items) Original receipt of 1788 and a 1796 copy, both signed by New York state auditor Peter J. Curtenius, re: collection of Quit Rents, paid by "Robert Livingston Esq. of the Manor" for a period 1765-1787, and received by Robert C. Livingston.
  - Letters, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    (2 items) Letters, re: a dispute over the rights to Livingston Manor: Letter from Chancellor Robert R. Livingston, at Clermont, to Robert Livingston Esq. of the Manor, dated 2 August 1790; Early Copy of Robert Livingston Esq.'s reply to the Chancellor, dated 2 September 1790.
  - Notes, circa 1795 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    (3 items) Notes, re: the survey and division of Livingston Manor after the death of Col. Robert Livingston, 3rd Lord of the Manor, in 1790: ND Note from Peter Van Schaick to John Livingston, c. 1795-1796, unsigned (possibly an early copy), re: offering recommendations to John Livingston for a defense against claim to lands "near to the Premises in Question," mentions "the Division in 1794"; ND List of Names – James Elliot, Duncan Thompson, John Dings [John Bingham?], John Wigram, John A. Fonda, Judge Woodworth, Teunis Van Vechten, Old Mr. Ten Broeck, Old Mr. Bleeker, John Loomis, Coenradt Clyne, Jacob Cline, William Melius, General Schuyler – with note, in a second hand, re: a land survey by Mr. Wigram; ND Note, unsigned (bottom of the sheet missing), re: apparently deposing Mr. Wigram, surveyor of Livingston Manor and collector of rents, of the details of a survey completed "with a view to accomplish an equal division of the Manor agreeable to the Will of the late Robert Livingston," mentions that 400 farms are contained within the Manor.
  - Judgment, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Judgment, dated 7 March 1797, affirming prior judgments of the New York State Supreme Court in two cases (the litigants names being partially illegible due to tears to the sheet), possibly "[Jerem]iah Schutt vs. [Jam]es Jackson ex dem: [Ma]ry Livingston" and "[Freder]ick Schutt vs. [James] Jackson ex dem: [Mary] Livingston", an early copy, addresses the State Senate and "the Hon Mr. Chancellor Livingston," mentions Chief Justice Robert Yates and Justices John Sloss Hobart and John Lansing Jr., hearers of the cases, and implies the signature of Bancker, the Clerk of the Court.
- Series 2: Five Nations Documents
  General
  The term "Brother Corlaer," found repeatedly in the following papers, was a form of address used generally by Indian delegations of the New York region during the 17th and 18th centuries towards their counterparts, the colonial governors and commissioners of Indian Affairs. The name comes from Arent Van Curler (1619-1667), a.k.a. Arent Van Corlaer, an early administrator of Rensselaerswyck who befriended the Native Americans and on several occasions successfully mediated between them and the colonists.
  - Processing note (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Processing note on envelope, unknown origin, "Papers, Indian Corrs., 1679-1700".
  - Onnondages reply to the Proposition of Colonel William Kendall, Agent of Virginia, 1679 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Onnondages reply to the Proposition of Colonel William Kendall, Agent of Virginia, in the Court House in Albany, 1 November 1679 [CG], in Dutch, an early copy [20th c. note, in pencil: "See Col. Hist N.Y., Vol. III, p. 324"].
  - Proposition made by the sachems of Schachtekook, complaining of the killing of their people, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Proposition made by the sachems of Schachtekook, complaining of the killing of their people (now 10 in number) [CG], in Dutch, dated January 1687, unsigned [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Vol. III, Col. Hist N.Y."].
  - Onnondages Soldiers Proposition with reply, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    (2 items) "Onnondages Soldiers Proposition," made at Albany, 28 June 1687, unsigned (probably an early copy), with reply by the Magistrates of Albany, 29 June 1687, and noting the Onondagas's response, re: threat of attack by the French from Canada, the Proposition witnessed by D. M[-], Johannes Wendel, Adriaen Gerritsen, Albert Ryckman, Levinus Van Schaick, Hendrick Cuyler [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Vol. III, Col. Hist N.Y."]; and an Account, 29 June 1687, of "ye Presents given by ye onnondages w were weigh'd in ye Court House" and of lead, powder, etc., given back to them.
  - Proposals made by the Magnase (Mohawk) sachems in Cachnaquage, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Proposals made by the Magnase (Mohawk) sachems in Cachnaquage, 1 July 1687, re: the capture of Johannes Roseboom and his party in jononda by the French and their Indians, written (and translated) by Dirck Wesselsz [CG], in Dutch [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Vol. III, Col. Hist N.Y."]
  - Governor Dongan's proposal to the Mohawk sachems, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Governor Dongan's proposal to the Mohawk sachems, Albany 10 July 14, 1687, pledging assistance to the Senecas "on this side of ye Lake" against attack by the French, appealing for cooperation among the Five Nations of the Iriquois (Mohawks, Oneidas, Onondagas, Cayugas and Senecas), expressing concern over the killing by "ye Brethren" of a "gentleman" in Virginia (lest they "make your friends your enemies"), unsigned, possibly a draft or early copy, with a note, re: gifts given to the Mohawks to be delivered to the Senecas [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Vol. III, Col. Hist N.Y."].
  - Memorandum of Francis, Lord Howard of Effingham, Governor of Virginia, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Memorandum of Francis, Lord Howard of Effingham, governor of Virginia, of a fatal skirmish and its aftermath, re: action occurring in Virginia at the head of James River, March 1687, involving a hunting party of Englishmen and Appomattock Indians who were ambushed by 60 or more "Seneca Indians" [Oneida See folder # 39, below], the memorandum signed and dated 13 July 1687 [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Vol. III, Col. Hist N.Y."
  - Account of the trading party of Captain Rooseboom, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Account of the trading party of Captain Rooseboom to Ottowa in the Fall of 1686, and of their capture and robbing at the hands of the French, from information taken at Albany, 16 July 1687, related by Caristasie and his brother, two Mohawk Indians of Capt. Roseboom's party [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Col. Hist N.Y., Vol. III – this is an interesting account"].
  - Examination of two Mohawk, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Examination of two Mohawk Indians "come from Canada who was in ye Company of Cryn" [Cryn, a.k.a Joseph (Sosé) Togouiroui, called the Great Mohawk, chief of the French Mohawks, d. 1690], taken in Albany by the Mayor and aldermen, 25 August 1687, re: efforts by the Governor of Canada at Montréal, the Jesuits, and Cryn to influence the Mohawks, Oneidas, and Onondagas not to make war with the French [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Vol. III, Col. Hist N.Y."].
  - Proposition made by Oneida sachems, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Proposition made by Oneida sachems to the Mayor and aldermen (the sachems having six prisoners with them), at City Hall in Albany, 3 September 1687, "with a Severe answer" to the sachems "for their wickedness in falling on Virginia People" (referring to Francis, Lord Howard of Effingham, governor of Virginia "who is come to N. Yorke for Satisfaction for ye mischief you have done" [see Memorandum, folder # 36, above]), and also the Indian's reply, on one sheet, signed by Robert Livingston (RL), those present: Mayor Pieter Schuyler, Dirck Wessels, Levinus Van Schaick, Hendrick Cuyler, Albert Ryckman, Adriaen Gerritsen, and [Keman] Jacobszen [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Col. Hist N.Y., Vol. III"].
  - Letter from Johannes Abeel, Mayor of Albany, 1695 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Letter from Johannes Abeel, Mayor of Albany, to Governor Benjamin Fletcher, dated Albany 11 August 1695, unsigned (perhaps a draft), re: Indians of the Five Nations moving towards Canada "for war," mentions the arrival of Captain Sands from Schenectady [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist N.Y."].
  - Processing note (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Processing note on envelope, unknown origin, "Indian Corrs., 1700-1723."
  - Propositions of three Onondaga messengers, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Propositions of three Onondaga messengers, made before and recorded by Robert Livingston at Albany, 11 June 1700, showing payment [given by Livingston] and his reply, re: a party of Seneca sachems "gone to Canada to speak there," a visiting delegation of Waganhae (Ottowa) sachems, and a request for more powder [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist N.Y."].